Guide to Technology, Culture and Society Papers RG.052
Poly Archives at the Bern Dibner Library of Science and Technology, NYU Libraries
Technology, Culture and Society Papers
1965-2017
Poly Archives at the Bern Dibner Library of Science and Technology, NYU Libraries
Polytechnic Institute of Brooklyn. Department of Technology, Culture and Society
RG.052
3 Linear Feet
Good
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was transferred to the Poly Archives by the Technology, Culture and Society Department in June 2022.
Arrangement
This collection is housed in five boxes and arranged into three series: Series I: Louis Menashe, 1965-1990 Series II: Humanities/Social Sciences, 1966-2017 Series III: Brooklyn Poly, 1983-2015. Original order was maintained whenever possible. However, there was some minor reorganization of materials for series placement.
Scope and Contents
The Technology, Society and Culture Papers contain documents from 1965-2017. These documents were assembled by Professors Sylvia Marks and Louis Menashe throughout their professional careers at Brooklyn Poly (operating under the names of Polytechnic Institute of Brooklyn (1900-1973), Polytechnic Institute of New York (1973-1985), Polytechnic University (1985-2008), and Polytechnic Institute of New York University). The collection's materials pertain to general Brooklyn Poly to the Technology, Society and Culture (TCS) department to Marks's and Menashe's work, specifically. A majority of the documents were produced for the Humanities/Social Sciences program at the, now non-existent, Famingdale campus. The collection contains professional writings, publications, and curriculum materials as well as personal writings and photographs. Documents include notes, correspondence, papers, and reprints. The collection is 3 linear feet, located on bay 29, shelves 3C and 4C.
Biographical / Historical
Technology, Culture and Society (TCS) is an academic department within NYU's Tandon School of Engineering. TCS promotes critical engagement with technology and science while drawing on the perspectives of the humanities and social sciences. Dr. Sylvia Kasey Marks is a professor of English within TCS, and previously served as Humanities Coordinator and Head of Freshman Writing at Polytechnic Institute's Long Island campus. Her research interests include British literature during the 18th century, history of the novel, and conduct literature. Dr. Louis Menashe is professor emeritus of Polytechnic University at NYU, where he was Charles S. Baylis Chair in History and headed the Social Sciences department. His research interests span Russian and Soviet history, as well as history in relation to cinema.
Polytechnic University (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.).; Social Sciences; Humanities; Soviet history, politics, society, and thought; Russian history and culture; Marks, Sylvia Kasey, 1943-; Menashe, Louis
- Series I: Louis Menashe, 1965-1990
  - Sub-series A: Drafts, undated
    - From Serfdom to High Politics: The Guchkovs of Moscow in Imperial Russia, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - The Guchkovs of Moscow: A Study in Bourgeois Development, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - How Not to Take Lenin Seriously: Profiles in the Soviet Experience from Lenin to Solzhenitsyn, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Sub-series B: Notes, 1986-1990
    - City of New York Landmarks Preservation Commission, Park Slope Notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Menashe CV Appendix, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Telephone Book, 1986-1990 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Sub-series C: Publications, 1965-1988
    - "A Liberal With Spurs": Alexander Guchkov, A Russian Bourgeois in Politics, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Cineaste, 1983-1988 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - In These Times, 1979-1984 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Book Reviews, 1970-1978 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - The Relevance of Leninism, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - The Real Paper, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Industrialists in Politics: Russia in 1905, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Commonweal, 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Present Tense, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Confronting Stalin's Ghost: The Soviet's Left Today, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Isaac Deutscher - In Memoriam, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Demystifying the Russian Revolution, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - The Modern Encyclopedia of Russian and Soviet History, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - The New York Times, 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - The Nation, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Newsday, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Historians Define the Baroque, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Understanding Glasnost: The Promises - The Paralysis, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Polytechnic Newspapers, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - "Stalker" Film Review, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Series II: Humanities/Social Sciences, 1966-2017
  - Sub-series A: Correspondence, 1968-2005
    - Correspondence, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - NAM, 1969-1976 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Postcards, 1969-2005 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Weinstein Correspondence, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence re: Robert V. Allen (Library of Congress), 1968 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Sub-series B: Curriculum, 1969-2017
    - Undergraduate Curriculum, 1986-2004 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Humanities and Social Science Requirements, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - NYU Colloquium, Spring 1970 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - SS161 and 221 Discussion Questions, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - SS161 - Last Years, USSR - Fall 2000 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - SS161 - Inside Gorbachev - Fall 2000 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - SS161 Fall 2000 New Publications, 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - SS161 Spring 1994, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Genovese: War on Two Fronts, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Fall 2017-Spring 2018 Course Listings (Box 5, Item 3)
  - Sub-series C: Events, 1980-1988
    - Culture Series I, 1986-1988 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Culture Series II, 1982-1986 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Culture Series III, 1980-1988 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Sub-series D: Examinations, 1966-1996
    - Michigan Test Answer Sheets I, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Willis, Basic Usage, Ex. 26A, #11-20 Answer Key, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Michigan Test Answer Sheets II, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Michigan Test Manual and Forms, 1968-1971 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Michigan Test Answer Sheets III, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Michigan Test Form E-K, 1966-1971 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Michigan Test Form L (I), 1971 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Michigan Test Form L (II), 1971 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - English Composition Placement Tests, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Placement Guidelines 1, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Placement Guidelines 2, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - NYU Polytechnic Examination Blue Blooks, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Sub-series E: Faculty, 1977-2011
    - Adjuncts 83-84, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Adjunct Applications 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Adjuncts 1982-83, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Adjuncts 1984-85, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Adjuncts 1985-86, 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Adjuncts 88-89, 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Spring '02 Adjuncts, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Summer 2002 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Adjunct Fall 2001 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Adjuncts 1990-91, 1989-1991 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Adjuncts 1989-90, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Adj Spring '92 Fall '92, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Adjuncts 1993-94, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Adjuncts 93-94, 1994-2011 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Adjuncts 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Adjuncts Spring '93, 1992-1993 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Adjuncts Spring 1995 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Adjuncts Fall '94, 1992-1994 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Adjuncts 1981-82, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Adjuncts 1980-1981, 1977-1981 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Adjuncts 1986-87, 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Adjuncts 1987-88, 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Sub-series F: News, 1991-1992
    - New York Times Clippings on U.S.S.R., 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Sub-series G: Reviews and Reports, 1969-1984-11-15
    - The Evolution of the Modern Merchant Ship by Commander M.W. Hirschkowitz, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Space Station Habitability Design Recommendations, Volume I, 1984-11-15 (Box 4, Item 1)
  - Sub-series H: Sylvia Marks, 1983-2010
    - Farmingdale Photographs, 1983-2004 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Sympathy Correspondence, 1990-2010 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Floppy Disks, undated (Box 5, Item 1)
    - Engraved Ornament, undated (Box 5, Item 2)
- Series III: Brooklyn Poly, 1983-2015
  - Sub-series A: Administrative, 1986-2004
    - Polytechnic Tuition Rates, 1986-2004 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Telephone Directory & Reports, 2001-2004 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Crisis Intervention Guide, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Pine Technical Notes, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Enrollment Figures, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Sub-series B: Events, 1983-2015
    - Long Island Convocation 1983-1985 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Student Council Annual Awards Banquet, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - NYU/Poly 4/4/2014 Student Award Ceremony CD, 2014-04-04 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - 1996 Handbook for Marshals and Commencement Assistants (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - 2015 Convocation Pamphlet (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Sub-series C: Memorabilia, 1987
    - Polytechnic University Commemorative Bookmarks, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Sub-series D: News, 1983-2014
    - "The Sun Sets at Farmingdale," The Polytechnic Reporter, 2002-05-01 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - New York Times Clippings, 1983-2014 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - George Bugliarello New York Times Obituary, 2011-02-02 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - U.S. News and World Report: America's Best Colleges, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Sub-series E: Programs, 2003-2008
    - Polytechnic University Writing Program Syllabi and Portfolio Guidelines, Spring 2008 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Bachelor of Science in Liberal Studies, 2003-2004 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Sub-series F: Student Organizations, 2004-2005
    - Performing Arts Club Playbills, 2004-2005 (Box 5, Folder 7)